Guide to the Maurepas collection, 1694-1749
Maurepas collection, 1694-1749
- Series III. Documents
  - 1743 - 1744
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Proposed compensations...to the Duc de Penthièvres] 1743 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D Provisions de Carême en 1743] [1743] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Languedoc. Députés. D Memoire des Députés au Conseil de Commerce sur le commerce d'Espagne et Indes Occidentales 1743 [n.p.], 12 ll. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Languedoc. Deputies. D [Report on commerce and manufacture of cloth to be sold in Spain and the West Indies] [1743] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Louis XV, King of France, 1710-1774 Edit du Roy... Paris, Imprimerie Royale, 1743., 4 ll. (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Michel, Gabriel DS Projet d'une expedition pour la mer du sud...Permission de la Cour d'Espagne 1743 [n.p.], 16 ll. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Report on Spanish trade and return of the treasure] [1743] [n.p.], 10 ll. (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Report on the commerce of Cadiz and Spanish America] [1743] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 D [Fonds extraordinaires 1743] [1743] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 D [Liste des officiers du département de Rochefort...] 1743 [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 AD [Memoire sur l'estat et les depenses de la marine] [1743] [n.p.], 4 ll. (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 D [Memoire sur les depenses de la marine] [1743] [n.p.], 5 ll. (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 D [Memoire sur les depenses de la marine en 1743] April 1743 [n.p.], 8 ll. (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Memoire en forme de journal de Mr. Matteus Genes] July 1743 [n.p.], 32 ll. (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Report of a secret agent concerning activities in Genoa...] July 1743 [Genoa], 3 ll. (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Cadiz. Merchants. DS Memoire de la nation Françoise établie Cadiz au sujet d'un projet tras contraire au commerce de France September 12, 1743 [Cadiz], 15 ll. (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Duvelaer, ALS to Maurepas September 26, 1743. Paris, 3 ll. (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Ollivier, Blaise-Joseph, 1701-1743 DS [Memoire sur l'estat ou sont les vaisseaux...] October 1, 1743 [Brest], 5 ll. (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - "1739" (Box 13, Folder 24-1)
    - "Sortis du grand portefeuille bleu Fontainbleau le 20 Octobre 1743." (Box 13, Folder 24-2)
    - Barry, L to Maurepas October 27, 1743. Agde, 2 ll. (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Liste des officiers choisis par le Roy pour servis sur les vaisseaux...] December 2, 1743. Versailles, 7 ll. (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - [Roussel de la Tour] D Richesse de l'Etat 1759? [n.p.], 9 ll. (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Papiers concernant les differents arrangements...pour assurer le retour en Espagne...1744/1745 (Box 13, Folder 28-1)
    - Papiers tirés du portefeuille de Mgr. le 6 May 1745 en partent pour Paris... (Box 13, Folder 28-2)
    - Gasquet, D Regles générales pour la construction... [ca. 1744] [Toulon], 23 ll. (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Louis XV, King of France, 1710-177 D [copy] Memoire du Roy pour servir d'instruction aud. de la Jonquière... [ca. 1744] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 D Affaires des prises juger... [1744-1745] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Conti, Louis Franpois de Bourbon, prince de, 1717-1776 D [Official account of the battle at Conty] [1744] [n.p.], 11 ll. (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Trésoriers Généraux des Galères...] [1744] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - 1744
    - Laffilard, D [Projets d'armement...] [1744] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - La Grande Chancel, AD [Memoire...nouvelle méthode de combattre nos enemies par mer...] [1744] [n.p.], 4 ll. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Le Clerc, D [Memoire concerning the French seizure of the Swedish ship, L'Assurance] [1744] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Le Clerc, D [Report on the seizure of the Swedish ship, L'Assurance, by a French corsair...] [1744] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Le Clerc, D [Report on treatment accorded Swedish vessels in previous wars...] [1744] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Mézières, Elenore-Marie-Thèrèse Oglethorpe, D [Reply to questions raised by Maurepas concerning her plan for the invasion of England] [1744] [n.p.], 4 ll. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Copy] [Plan to attack British ships at Port Mahon] [1744] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 AD Extrait des ordres [et] observations [1744], 4 ll. (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D Memoire pour les trésoriers... April 26, 1744. Paris, 7 ll. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D Les tresoriers généraux... April 26, 1744. Paris, 2 ll. (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 D [Memoire sur les operations de la marine dans la mediterannée...] June 10, 1744. [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Fonds extraordinaires accordés par le Roy pour les armements de 1743 et 1744] July 1744 [n.p.], 8 ll. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Projet d'instruction au S. de Nesmond capitaine de vaisseau] [July 1744] [n.p.], 5 ll. (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Projet d'instruction pour M. de Rochambeau chef d'escadre] [July 1744] [n.p.], 4 ll. (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Toulon. Armements, l'escadre de Toulon] July 10, 1744. Dunkerque, 6 ll. (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Toulon. Armements. Le Roy d'Espagne a donné ordre...] July 17, 1744. Dunkerque, 3 ll. (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Liste des vaisseaux du Roy...] August 1744 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Marine. Armement. La liste qui est ci-joint...] August 1744 [n.p.], 5 ll. (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Memoire des vaisseaux du Roy...] August 1744 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Prussia. Minister. D [Memoire concerning French seizure of the "Demoiselle Marianne"] August 4, 1744. [Metz], 1 l. (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 AD [Explanation of abstract of orders to be sent from the Spanish court to Torres] August 12, [1744] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Prussia. Minister. D [Memoire concerning the seizure of the Prussian ship, "Philippe"] September 8, 1744. Metz, 1 l. (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Instructions for de Piosin based on answers received from the Spanish court] November 1744 [n.p.], 6 ll. (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Memoire sur la nouvelle destination donnée aux escadres commandées par Mr. de Piosin et de la Jonquière] November 1744 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [copy] Projet d'instruction pour M. de la Jonquière November 1744 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Instructions for de Piosin based on answers received from the Spanish court] November 2, 1744. [n.p.], 6 ll. (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Concerns case of the ship, La Lievende...] [ca. 1745] [n.p.] (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Report on trade, to serve as a preliminary study for compilation of laws and commercial regulations for the Kingdom of Naples] [1745-1749] [n.p.], 72 ll. (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Paris. Académie Royale de Musique. Opéra. D [Note concerning S. Lany...] [1745?] [Paris], 1 l. (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Thomond, Charles II O'Brien, viscount Clare, earl of, 1699-1761 D [Etat de ce qui est embarquée sur le senau Le Prince Charles] [ca. 1745] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Thomond, Charles II O'Brien, viscount Clare, earl of, 1699-1761 D [Estat des farines embarquées sur les batiments...] [ca. 1745-1746] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Arnault du Clavier, ADS [Dissertation sur un entretien avec les principaux commis de la marine...] [1745] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Arnault du Clavier, ADS [Essay sur le commerce exterieur de France par les ports de mer] [1745] [n.p.], 6 ll. (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Bonnet, Jean-Baptiste ADS [Suggestions for raising funds for the navy by new methods of taxation] [1745] [Marseilles], 4 ll. (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Dupin, Joseph D [Concerns booty captured by a captain of a ship owned by Dupin] [1745] [Bayonne], 4 ll. (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Fournier, D [Memoire pour faire connoitre la situation actuelle du commerce...] ]1745] [n.p.], 22 ll. (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Marine 1744. Extrait du depense de l'exercise de 1744] [1745] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Memoire sur l'estat actuel de la marine...de l'année 1745] [1745] [n.p.], 13 ll. (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 AD [Projet de la destination que l'on pourra donner aux 23 vaisseaux...] [1745] [n.p.], 6 ll. (Box 14, Folder 39)
  - 1745 - 1746
    - Sisley [?] D [Memoire sur les moyens de procurer au Roy...] [1745] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Thomond, Charles II O'Brien, viscount Clare, earl of, 1699-1761 DS [Memoire pour Pierre Picquet proprietaire de la fregatte, La Charité de Dunkerque] [1745] [Dunkerque], 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Copy of memoire sent to Campo-Florida] January 19, 1745. [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Copy of orders given to De Piosin] January 19, 1745 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Colonies. Suivant le projet d'arrangement pour les dépenses...] February 1745 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Freiburg, Battle of, L (in unknown handwriting) to Maurepas June 5, 1745. Freiburg, 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Paris. Académie royale de Musique. (Opéra) D [Listing of questions and rulings made by the council] June 10, 1745 [Paris], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 D [Memorandum on proposed expedition to Scotland...] [August 25, 1745] [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Pellerin, Joseph, 1684-1782 D [Extrait de differents nouvelles concernant la marine] July 18, 1745 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Rebel, Francois, 1701-1775 D [Listing of bonuses for artists of the Opéra for the year 1744-1745] [August 1745] [Paris], 4 ll. (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 D [Note concerning distribution of bonuses at the Opéra] August 11, 1745 [Versailles], 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Bigot, Francois D [Relation du siège de Louisbourg] August 15, 1745 [n.p.], 12 ll. (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Marine. Dettes des anciens exercises...] Septembre 1745 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Fournier, D [Reflexions sur les moyens de sauver le debris du commerce en France...] [October 1745] [n.p.], 11 ll. (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Lépine, Guillaume Joseph de, [fl. 1740- ] D [copy] Certificate regarding illness of Mlle. Rotisset de Romainville October 3, 1745. Paris, 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - O'Heguarty, Pierre André, 1700-1763 ADS [Outline for a project to intervene in Ireland in favor of the Stuarts] October 14, 1745. Paris, 13 ll. (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - O'Heguarty, Pierre André, 1700-1763 D [Projet pour renouveller le Gouvernment de la Grande Bretagne...] [October 15, 1745] [Paris], 11 ll. (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Vincelles, Mme. La Ferrière D [Request for a pension...] November 1745 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Marine 1745. Extrait des depenses de la marine...] November 28, 1745. [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Langerie, AD [Request to be named Commissaire des classes of Languedoc] [December 1745] [Marseilles], 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - d'Albert du Antoine Chesne, Chevalier, 1686-1751 D [Recommendations...] [1746?] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - d'Albert du Antoine Chesne, Chevalier, 1686-1751 D [Review of his career] [1746?] [n.p.], 5 ll. (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Enville, Nicolas de la Rochefoucauld, duc d', 17__-1746 AD [Observations...] [ca. 1746] [n.p.], 9 ll. (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Copie d'art. 7 du traité conclu Utrecht le 11 Avril 1713...] [1746?] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Thomond, Charles II O'Brien, viscount Clare, earl of, 1699-1761 D [Concerns case of a Scot, Bostwick, wrongly imprisoned] [ca. 1746] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Fournier, D [Memoire sur les moyens de trouver des fonds pour retablir la marine du Roy] 1746 [n.p.], 11 ll. (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Extrait des sommes denuëes la marine] January 1746 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Plan for the establishment of a French commercial settlement in Chile] [1746] [n.p.], 39 ll. (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de, 1701-1781 D [Reply to the Prussian Minister...] [1746] [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - [Memoire pour Jean-Baptiste Dupont, capitaine du Corsaire de l'Attrape si tu peux...] Paris, 1746., 14 ll. (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - Payot, DS [Memoire pour servir de reforme au commerce que les francais font dans le continent de l'Espagne] [1746] [Valencia] (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Romieu D [Report on the seizure of "La Ville de Rotterdam..."] [1746] [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Vernet, D [Report on the seizure of a Russian ship...] [1746] [Paris], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - Thomond, Charles II O'Brien, viscount Clare, earl of, 1699-1761 DS [Etat des piquets de la Brigade Irlandaises...] January 16, 1746. Calais, 2 ll. (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Memorandum on convoy ships leaving Ostende and Dunkerque] [February-March 1746] [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Recapitulation général de tous les vaisseaux anglois...] February 1, 1746. [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Thomond, Charles II O'Brien, viscount Clare, earl of, 1699-1761 D [Report on voyage of Captain Bachelier to Scotland] March 1746 [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Report on French commercial interests and how to protect them at the peace conference] [June 1746] [n.p.], 12 ll. (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - 1746 - 1751
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Memoire sur divers articles concernant le commerce de l'Espagne] September 1746 [n.p.], 72 ll. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Estat de la depense de la marine d'Angleterre] November 1746 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Memoire sur l'estat actuel de la marine... ] November 1746 [n.p.], 32 ll. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - [France. Ministère de la Marine] D [Relation de tout ce qui c'est passé dans la flote de monsieur de l'Etanduère;] [November 1746] [Paris], 4 ll. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Liste generale des vaisseaux du Roy avec leur destinations] November 1, 1746 [n.p.], 3 ll. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Fonds demandés pour 1747 sans armement d'autres vaisseaux que les garde-côtes] November 8, 1746 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Note des vaisseaux qui peuvent estre armes in Ponant en Janvier et Fevrier] November 8, 1746 [n.p.], 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Projet de ce qu'il en cousterois pour l'armement des Batiments... ] [c. 1747] n.p., 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Talmond, Anne-Charles Frédéric de la Tremoille, prince de DS [Le Roi de Pologne m'a proposé.. .] [c.1747] [n.p.], 8 ll. (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Boyer d'Eguilles, Alexandre J-B, marquis de AD [Memoire sur les moyens de faire avec succes un tentative sur l'Ecosse.. .] [1747] [n.p.], 10 ll. (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Laffilard DS [Inventaire des ordonnances... ] [1747] [n.p.] (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - [Talmond, Anne-Charles Frédéric de la Tremoille, prince de] D [Nous soussignés Anne-Charles.. .] [1747] [n.p.], 9 ll. (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - [Talmond, Anne-Charles Frédéric de la tremoille, prince de,] D [[copy] Nous soussignés.. .] January 1747 [n.p.], 11 ll. (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Herouville de Claye, Antoine, comte de;, 1713-1782 ADS [ Memoire pour la campagne de l'année 1747] January 3, 1747 Paris, 8 ll. (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Laffilard DS [Bureau de Levant et Ponant] January 10, 1747 Paris, 2 ll. (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Laffilard DS [Bureau des classes... ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Laffilard DS [Bureau des colonies... ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Laffilard DS [Bureau des Fonds... ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Laffilard DS [Bureau du Commerce et Pais Etrangères... ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Laffilard DS [Etat des papiers concernant les prises... ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 1 l. (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Laffilard DS [Inventaire des papiers du bureau du depôt... ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 4 l. (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Laffilard DS [Ministres et secretaires d'état... ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 4 ll. (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Laffilard DS [Ordres pour le deposit de la Marine ] January 10, 1747 Paris, 2 ll. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [ Memoire concernant les armements qui peuvent se faire Toulon et Marseille] April 1747 [n.p.], 7 ll. (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Naval preparations in Provence - galleys] April 17, 1747 [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Pallavicini, Gianluca D [Report on the Corsican situation] [October 29, 1747] [Paris], 5 ll. (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Richelieu, Louis Franlois Armand du Plessis, duc de;, 1696-1788 D [News of the war] December 8, 1747 Genoa, 7 ll. (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Inseignes de Vaisseau] [1749?] [n.p.], 28 ll. (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. M "Livre contenant les principes de la navigation" [c. 1749] [n.p.], 87 ll. (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [Liste des capitaines des vaisseaux suivant leur rang et ancienneté] [c. 1749] [n.p.], 18 ll. (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - France. Ministère de la Marine. D [ Liste des officiers generaux suivant leur ancienneté] July 16, 1749 [n.p.], 2 ll. (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Calais. Admiralty. D [ Ruling on the case of Isaac Robert;.. .] [c. 1751] [Calais], 2 ll. (Box 16, Folder 32)